Finding Aid for Alfred Merle Beeton Papers 1952-1994
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Alfred Merle Beeton Papers
1952-1994
Beeton, Alfred Merle, 1927-
Alfred M. Beeton was a professor at the University of Michigan specializing in limnology, the study of the biology, chemistry, and physics of freshwater lakes. The papers reflect Beeton's primary interest in the limnology and preservation of the St. Lawrence Great Lakes, with an emphasis on factors affecting water quality and eutrophication, i.e. the lack of oxygen--and concomitant death of fish--in lakes due to over-enrichment. The papers also highlight Beeton's ongoing interests in the opossum shrimp, Mysis Relicta, and his extensive work as a consultant and administrator on projects relating to these topics.
0399 Aa 2
12.66 linear feet
Bentley Historical Library University of Michigan
Dr. Beeton (Donor no. 8563 ) donated his papers to the library in 1997.
The collection is open for research.
Alfred M. Beeton is a leading researcher in the study of the St. Lawrence Great Lakes, along the U.S.-Canadian border. In addition to academic careers at the University of Michigan and the University of Wisconsin-Milwaukee, Beeton has served in a number of positions as an investigator for and advisor to organizations making policy for the Great Lakes.
Born in 1927, Beeton moved to Michigan as a child. He received his B.S., (1952) M.S., (1954) and Ph.D. (1958) degrees from the University of Michigan, specializing in limnology and aquatic zoology. He began teaching in the years immediately preceding and following his doctorate, acting as a teaching fellow, instructor, and lecturer at the University of Michigan and Wayne State University from 1952 to 1961. Also during this time period, Beeton began work as a researcher at the U.S. Bureau of Commercial Fisheries Great Lakes Fisheries Laboratory, where he was among the first scientists raising the alarm about the 'death' of Lake Erie due to pollution. Working at the Laboratory from 1957 to 1966, Beeton was promoted to Chief of the Laboratory's Environmental Research Program in 1959, a position which he held until he moved on to an academic appointment at the University of Wisconsin-Milwaukee.
From 1966 to 1976 Beeton served as a professor and administrator at UW-Milwaukee. In addition to his academic appointment, Beeton also was the Associate Director of the University's Center for Great Lakes Studies from 1966 to 1973, and Associate Dean for Research in the Graduate School from 1973 to his move back to Michigan in 1976. In these capacities, Beeton was highly-sought after as a consultant. While at Wisconsin, Beeton also served as a consultant to the U.S. Army Corps of Engineers, studying the effect of Corps' dredging activities on pollution in the Great Lakes (1968-1970). He also served as an expert witness for the City of Chicago and the State of Minnesota (et al.) in litigation against various steel, mining, and electric companies for their pollution of Lakes Michigan and Superior (1968-1974). Additionally, Beeton worked as a member of numerous committees regarding the Great Lakes, and as head of the International Biological Program's task force to identify Michigan, Minnesota, and Wisconsin aquatic areas for preservation.
Moreover, Beeton contributed to a number of governmental projects during this time period, notably the U.S. Government's Foreign Currency Program, as a limnological researcher. In addition to serving as a consultant for various Environmental Protection Agency projects from 1973 to 1983, Beeton was the Principal Investigator on limnological studies of Lake Skadar, Yugoslavia, from 1975 to 1982 as part of the Smithsonian Institution's Foreign Currency Program. Beeton also worked with the Foreign Currency Program as an investigator on an earlier phase of the Skadar project, from 1972 to 1974, and on projects in India, Israel, and Pakistan from 1963 to 1965, when the Program was under the auspices of the U.S. Bureau of Commercial Fisheries.
After moving back to Michigan, Beeton was a professor and administrator at the University of Michigan from 1976 to 1986. His duties included teaching appointments with the School of Natural Resources and the College of Engineering, the Directorships of both the University's Great Lakes and Marine Waters Center and its Michigan Sea Grant College Program, and memberships in various committees. Notably, Beeton was Chair of the NOAA/GLERL Building Committee. (GLERL is the National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration's Great Lakes Environmental Research Laboratory, stationed in Ann Arbor. The Building Committee planned the creation of GLERL's new building on the University of Michigan's North Campus.) Beeton continued his outside professional work during this time period, working with such organizations as the National Sea Grant Association (and serving as its President from 1983 to 1984), and the International Joint Commission for the Great Lakes.
In 1986, Beeton left full-time teaching, and from 1986 to 1996 served as the Director of GLERL. He continued teaching part-time, holding Adjunct professorships with the School of Public Health, the School of Natural Resources, and the College of Engineering. He continued his professional work, for example serving from 1986 to 1991 as Co-chairman of the International Joint Commission for the Great Lakes' Science Advisory Board, and from 1987 to 1989 as a Commissioner on the State of Michigan's Toxic Substance Control Commission. In 1996, Beeton retired from GLERL, and from 1996 through the time of accession of his papers (1997), he served as Acting Chief Scientist for NOAA.
The papers of Alfred Beeton--while covering his entire career from his days as a graduate-student teaching fellow to his Directorship of the National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration's Great Lakes Environmental Research Laboratory--are most comprehensive in their documentation of Beeton's activities from 1966 to 1976, during his tenure at the University of Wisconsin-Milwaukee. Nevertheless, the papers give insight into Beeton's long career, with its wide range of interests and numerous activities. The collection is organized into eight series: Correspondence, Professional Activities and Inquiries, Drafts of and Information on Talks and Manuscripts, Course Material, Army Corps of Engineers Dredging Studies, Toxic Substance Control Commission, Court Activities and Depositions, and Topical.
Subjects:
Beeton, Alfred Merle, 1927-; Limnology--Michigan.; Limnology--Great Lakes.; Limnologists.; Michigan. Toxic Substance Control Commission.; University of Michigan--Faculty.; University of Wisconsin--Milwaukee--Faculty.; United States. Army. Corps of Engineers.; Water--Pollution--Great Lakes.
- Correspondence, 1966-1976
  The series Correspondence (1966-1976), shares considerable overlap with the series Professional Activities and Inquiries (1966-1975). It consists largely of general correspondence that Beeton collected into binders for future reference.
  - 1966 (Box 1)
  - 1967 (Box 1)
  - December 1966-December 1969 (Box 1)
    (formerly in binder)
  - 1969-1970 (Box 1)
  - 1971 (Box 1)
  - General, 1971 (Box 1)
  - 1971-1972 (Box 1)
  - 1972 (Box 1)
  - General, 1972-1973 (Box 1)
  - 1973-February 1975 (Box 1)
  - Personal, 1956-1974 (Box 2)
  - Miscellaneous, 1969-1976 (Box 2)
- Professional Activities and Inquiries, 1966-1975
  The Professional Activities and Inquiries (1966-1975) series shares considerable overlap with the first, Correspondence (1966-1976). It consists of correspondence and information that Beeton used to support yearly activity reports to the University administration.
  - Activities, 1966-1975; 9 folders (Box 2)
  - Professional Opinions, 1968-1974; 5 folders (Box 2)
  - Other, 1968-1974; 4 folders (Box 2)
- Drafts of and Information on Talks and Manuscripts, 1952-1991
  The series Drafts of and Information on Talks and Manuscripts (1952-1991) consists of drafts of Beeton's manuscripts and talks. It also includes background material such as correspondence on and supporting data for those drafts, and revisions and re-workings of the drafts for publication or adaptation to new purposes (e.g. the Encyclopedia Britannica article that was adapted into the script for a documentary). The materials in this series give specific examples of Beeton's research interests and scholarly work.
  - AAAS Paper, 1970-1971 (Box 2)
  - Aging of the Great Lakes, 1965 (Box 2)
  - Air Toxics Conference, October 7-9, 1987 (Box 2)
  - Airborne Infrared Survey of Lake Erie, 1963-1969 (Box 2)
  - "Antennal Scale Length as a Measure of Relative Size in M. Relicta "-Submitted Am. Midl. Nat., June 1976 (Box 2)
  - China Trip Information, 1985-1986 (Box 2)
  - "Effects of Eutrophication on Fish"-NE Fish and Wildlife Conference, May 1972 (Box 2)
  - Ecosystems Manuscript, 1988 (Box 2)
  - Encyclopedia Britannica Article and Script for Movie-"Aging of a Lake"-Beeton and Ballart, 1969-1972 (Box 2)
  - Eutrophication of Large Lakes-SCOL Paper, 1968-1971 (Box 3)
  - Great Lakes Limnological Program, 1952-1959 (Box 3)
  - "Indices of Great Lakes Eutrophication", 1965-1966 (Box 3)
  - Lake Michigan Grab Comparison Studies (Box 3)
  - Lake Superior Conference, 1976 (Box 3)
  - "The Laurentian Great Lakes", 1969-1970 (Box 3)
  - "Microbial Degradation of TFM" Research Proposal, 1971-1974 (Box 3)
  - Miscellaneous, circa 1950s (Box 3)
  - Miscellaneous, circa 1970s-1980s (Box 3)
  - Mysid Bibliography, 1962-1984 (Box 3)
  - Mysis Relicta
    - Correspondence, 1955-1980 (Box 3)
    - Horizontal Distribution and Life History (Box 3)
    - "Horizontal Distribution and Abundance of M. Relicta in Lake Michigan", 1977-1978 (Box 3)
    - Materials for 1989 Manuscript, 1981-1991 (Box 3)
  - Saginaw Bay
    - Benthos, 1969 (Box 3)
    - Hydrography, 1956-1961 (Box 3)
    - Physical Limnology, 1958-1969 (Box 3)
  - St. Lawrence Great Lakes Chapter, 1956-1962 (Box 3)
  - Teach In, 1969-1970 (Box 3)
  - University of California Berkeley WREES Lectures, 1970-1971 (Box 3)
- Course Material, 1954-1973
  Course Material (1954-1973) consists of syllabi, lecture notes, and exams for courses Beeton taught while as an instructor at the University of Michigan and Wayne State University, and as a Professor at the University of Wisconsin-Milwaukee. It also includes some work by Beeton's students.
  - Aquatic Biology Seminar (Zoology 928)
    - Fall 1971 (Box 3)
    - Spring 1973 (Box 3)
    - Fall 1973 (Box 3)
  - Aquatic Microbiology (Zoology 611), Spring 1973 (Box 3)
  - Eastward Cruise (Zoology 990), 1969 (Box 3)
  - Embryology (Zoology 82), 1954-1957 (Box 3)
  - Human Anatomy (Zoology 152), circa 1950s (Box 3)
  - Limnology Exams and Notes (Box 4)
  - Limnology Lecture Notes (Box 4)
  - Limnology Seminar (Zoology 970), Spring 1968 (Box 4)
  - Microbiology Seminar (C.E. 680), 1962-1964 (Box 4)
  - Wayne State and University of Michigan Limnology Student Work, 1958-1961 (Box 4)
- Army Corps of Engineers Dredging Studies, 1963-1972
  The series Army Corps of Engineers Dredging Studies (1963-1972) documents Beeton's work on the Board of Consultants to the U.S. Army Corps of Engineers project studying the effect of Corps' dredging activities on pollution in the Great Lakes. It includes background material, preliminary reports on numerous harbors, and the project's final report.
  - Correspondence, 1963-1969 (Box 4)
  - Functional Testing Contract (Box 4)
  - Harbor Information
    - Reviews of Data (Box 4)
    - Green Bay, 1966-1967 (Box 4)
    - Lake Ontario Great Sodus Bay, 1967-1968 (Box 4)
    - Lorain, Ohio (Box 4)
    - Michigan and Wisconsin Studies not in Pilot Survey, 1967-1968 (Box 4)
    - Rouge River, Detroit, 1967-1968 (Box 4)
  - Meeting Minutes, 1967-1968 (Box 4)
  - Miscellaneous, 1966-1968 (Box 4)
  - Questions for Consultants (Box 4)
  - Surveys and Reports, 1967; Undated (Box 4)
  - Surveys and Reports, 1968 (Box 4)
  - Surveys and Reports-Lake Surveys, 1968 (Box 4)
  - Final Report Drafts
    - Documents for Final Report (Box 4)
    - Outline and Sections for Board of Consultants (Box 4)
    - Revisions by Consultants (Box 5)
  - Engineering Feasibility Study on Provision of Alternate Disposal Areas for 15 Lake Erie Harbors, February 1966 (Box 5)
  - Engineering Feasibility Study on Selected Treatment Processes for Great Lakes Dredgings, December 1968 (Box 5)
  - Preliminary Report on Effects of Spoil Disposal at Alpena, Michigan Harbor (Box 5)
  - Preliminary Report on Effects of Spoil Disposal at Ashtabula, Ohio Harbor (Box 5)
  - Preliminary Report on Effects of Spoil Disposal at Erie, Pennsylvania Harbor (Box 5)
  - Preliminary Report on Effects of Spoil Disposal at Frankfort, Michigan Harbor (Box 5)
  - Preliminary Report on Effects of Spoil Disposal at Indiana, Indiana Harbor (Box 5)
  - Preliminary Report on Effects of Spoil Disposal at Lorain, Ohio Harbor (Box 5)
  - Preliminary Report on Effects of Spoil Disposal at Manistee, Michigan Harbor (Box 5)
  - Dredging and Water Quality Problems in the Great Lakes
    - Report (Box 5)
    - Appendices (Box 6)
    - Appendix K: Alternate Disposal Areas (Box 6)
  - Buffalo District, 1968-1972 (Box 6)
  - Buffalo District Contract No. DACW 49-72-C-0010, 1971-1972 (Box 6)
  - Diversion Report, 1968-1971 (Box 6)
  - Smithsonian Report on Disposal of Dredge Spoil, 1971-1972 (Box 6)
- Toxic Substance Control Commission, 1986-1989
  The Toxic Substance Control Commission (1986-1989) series documents Beeton's membership in and the work of this Commission, created by the State of Michigan in 1978 as an independent board of scientists to act as ombudsmen for Michigan citizens concerned about the State's handling of issues regarding toxic substances. Other than the work of the Commission, of particular note in the series is the documentation relating to the end of the Commission, which resigned en mass after Governor James Blanchard repeatedly cut its funding, changed its reporting lines, and failed to support its recommendations.
  - Preliminary Material, December 1986-February 1987 (Box 6)
  - Executive Secretary Reports, December 1986-February 1987 (Box 6)
  - Tributyl Tin (TBT), April-May 1987 (Box 6)
  - Meeting Items, February 1987-March 1988; 9 folders (Box 6)
  - Meeting Items, April 1988-September 1989; 17 folders (Box 7)
  - Correspondence and Information, February 1987-January 1988; 7 folders (Box 7)
  - Correspondence and Information, January 1988-November 1989; 19 folders (Box 8)
  - Final Meeting Items, December 14, 1989 (Box 8)
- Court Activities and Depositions, 1965-1974
  The series Court Activities and Depositions (1965-1974) highlights Beeton's work as an expert witness in Great-Lakes pollution litigation. The first file relates to Beeton's work for the City of Chicago and State of Illinois in cases against Commonwealth Edison, U.S. Steel, Republic Steel, and Inland Steel. The second file relates to his work for the State of Minnesota (et al.) against Reserve Mining Corporation.
  - Metropolitan Sanitation District of Greater Chicago
    - vs. Commonwealth Edison, 1969-1972 (Box 8)
    - vs. Inland Steel, 1968-1972 (Box 8)
    - vs. Inland Steel et al. Beeton Deposition, May 5, 1972 (Box 9)
    - And State of Illinois vs. Inland Steel
      - Reports, 1973-1974 (Box 9)
      - Bramer Report, 1974 (Box 9)
    - Miscellaneous (Indiana Harbor and Calumet Harbor), 1968-1974 (Box 9)
    - vs. Republic Steel, 1972-1973 (Box 9)
    - vs. US Steel-Report of Proceedings, July 23-24, 1970 (Box 9)
    - vs. US Steel, 1969-1974 (Box 9)
  - Minnesota / Reserve Mining Case
    - Correspondence and Information, 1972-1973 (Box 9)
    - Research Reports, 1965-1973 (Box 9)
    - Court Documents and Depositions, February-July 1973 (Box 9)
    - Beeton Deposition and Exhibits, March 29, 1973 (Box 9)
    - Taconite Project Binder (Beeton Deposition Exhibit 12) (Box 9)
- Topical, 1955-1994
  The most diverse series, Topical (1955-1994), covers the length and breadth of Beeton's career. It includes documentation of his international activities, examples of data collected on research vessel expeditions, his work as a consultant to such organizations as the Environmental Protection Agency and the International Joint Commission for the Great Lakes, and his tenure at several Great Lakes centers, such as University of Michigan's Great Lakes and Marine Waters Center, NOAA's Great Lakes Environmental Research Laboratory, and the University of Wisconsin-Milwaukee's Center for Great Lakes Studies.
  - AEC Proposal
    - Contract 2158-Influence of Thermal Discharge...on Temperature and Near-Shore Circulation, 1971-1973 (Box 9)
    - Contract 2160-Influence of Thermal Discharge...on Biology and Near-Shore Circulation, 1971-1975 (Box 9)
  - Beeton (Box 9)
  - Center for Great Lakes Studies, 1971-1976 (Box 9)
  - Center for the Great Lakes, 1988 (Box 9)
  - Coding and Processing Data, 1961-1966 (Box 10)
  - Coding-Endex Coding of Hydrographic Data Sources, 1972-1974 (Box 10)
  - Data and Graphs
    - Bureau of Commercial Fisheries Research Vessel Reports and Data
      - CISCO Field Notebook, 1956 (Box 10)
      - CISCO Cruise Reports, 1955-1963 (Box 10)
      - CISCO Physical-Chemical Data, 1963 (Box 10)
      - CISCO Ship's Log, 1963 (Box 10)
      - GEORGE L / MUSKY II Cruise Reports, 1959-1962 (Box 10)
      - KAHO Bathythermograph Log, 1963 (Box 10)
      - KAHO Cruise Map, 1963 (Box 10)
      - KAHO Fathometer Tracings, 1963 (Box 10)
      - KAHO Field Notes, 1963 (Box 10)
      - KAHO Mixed Sediment Data, 1963 (Box 10)
      - KAHO Sediment Cores, 1963 (Box 10)
      - SISCOWET Cruise Reports, 1958-1963 (Box 10)
    - Green Bay Drift Bottle Cards, 1959-1960 (Box 10)
    - Lab Methods (Box 10)
    - Lake Michigan Productivity Study
      - C-14 Logging Sheets, 1970 (Box 10)
      - Communications among Staff, 1970 (Box 10)
      - Conductivity Data-Milwaukee-Ludington Car Ferry, 1970-1971 (Box 10)
    - Lake Ontario (Box 10)
    - Sylvania Lakes (Box 10)
  - Department of Natural Resources Oligochaeta Study, 1972-1975 (Box 10)
  - Electric Power Research Institute Workshop
    - Impact of Power Plants, 1975 (Box 10)
    - Impact Assessment, 1980 (Box 10)
  - EPA
    - Atmospheric Phosphorous, 1973-1975 (Box 10)
    - Chlorination Project, 1971-1975 (Box 10)
    - Environmental Research Lab Reorganization
      - Correspondence, 1983 (Box 10)
      - Science Advisory Board Site Visits
        - Gulf Breeze, 1983 (Box 10)
        - Narragansett, 1983 (Box 10)
      - Reports, 1982-1983 (Box 10)
    - Lake Michigan Monitoring Plan, 1973-1976 (Box 11)
    - NOAA-Green Bay Management Committee, 1987-1992 (Box 11)
    - NOAA-Green Bay Management Committee-Reports, 1988-1990 (Box 11)
    - Reviews of Reports, 1973-1974 (Box 11)
  - Fish Work Group, Great Lakes Basin Committee, 1970 (Box 11)
  - Foreign Activities
    - Bimini Proposal (Bahamas) (Box 11)
    - Foreign Currency Program, 1962-1966 (Box 11)
    - Foreign Currency Program-India and Pakistan, 1963-1968 (Box 11)
    - Skadar Lake, Yugoslavia
      - Preliminary Proposals and Material, 1973-1975 (Box 11)
      - Progress Report, 1974 (Box 11)
      - Correspondence, 1976 (Box 11)
      - Correspondence, 1977 (Box 11)
      - Macrophyte Section of Report, 1978-1980 (Box 11)
      - Follow-up and Monograph Preparation, 1978-1983 (Box 11)
    - Smithsonian-India, 1972-1974 (Box 11)
    - U.N. Food and Agriculture Organization, 1965-1972 (Box 11)
  - Fredonia Board of Visitors / Lake Erie, 1969 (Box 11)
  - Great Lakes Fishery Commission, 1962-1977 (Box 11)
  - Great Lakes and Marine Waters Center, 1977-1983 (Box 11)
  - Great Lakes Research Proposal-NSF, 1985-1986 (Box 11)
  - Great Lakes Research Symposium, 1968 (Box 11)
  - HR 35 Statement, 1975-1976 (Box 12)
  - Huron River Watershed Council, 1989-1990 (Box 12)
  - Ideas for Research (Box 12)
  - International Association for Great Lakes Research, 1966-1968 (Box 12)
  - International Biological Program, 1970-1973 (Box 12)
  - International Biological Program-Newsletters, 1969-1972 (Box 12)
  - International Joint Commission for the Great Lakes
    - Committee on Eutrophication, 1972-1974 (Box 12)
    - Science Advisory Board, 1985-1986 (Box 12)
    - Biennial Meeting on Water Quality, 1991 (Box 12)
  - International Limnology Congress 1962-Participant Tour Planning, 1960-1962 (Box 12)
  - JURUE Conference, 1980 (Box 12)
  - JURUE Conference-Background Material for Paper, 1979-1980 (Box 12)
  - Lake Erie Literature, 1958-1966 (Box 12)
  - Limnological Systems Analysis of the Great Lakes, 1971-1972 (Box 12)
  - NASA-Remote Sensing of Chlorophyll, 1971 (Box 12)
  - NOAA
    - Cooperative Institute for Great Lakes Research Proposal, 1978 (Box 12)
    - Great Lakes Environmental Research Lab, 1990-1993 (Box 12)
    - Great Lakes Environmental Research Lab-Planning for New Building, 1974-1981 (Box 12)
    - Great Lakes Environmental Research Lab-Meeting with Architects, 1980-1981 (Box 12)
    - Great Lakes Environmental Research Lab-Priorities Workshop, 1974 (Box 12)
    - Great Lakes Environmental Research Lab-Zebra Mussel Activities, 1992-1993 (Box 12)
    - Great Lakes Environmental Research Lab-Zebra Mussel Activities-Background Material, 1990-1991 (Box 12)
    - Great Lakes Environmental Research Lab-Zebra Mussel Activities-Conferences, 1992-1994 (Box 12)
  - Ocean and Coastal Resource Act of, 1976 (Box 12)
  - Oceanographic Instruments for Research Vessels, 1961 (Box 12)
  - Research Vessels (Box 12)
  - Reviews of Manuscripts and Proposals, 1976-May 1978 (Box 12)
  - Reviews of Manuscripts and Proposals, June-December 1978 (Box 13)
  - Reviews of Manuscripts and Proposals, 1979-1980 (Box 13)
  - Reviews of Manuscripts and Proposals, 1981-1984 (Box 13)
  - Reviews of Manuscripts and Proposals, 1985-1986 (Box 13)
  - School of Natural Resources Development Plan, 1983 (Box 13)
  - Sea Grant Program, 1970-1971 (Box 13)
  - South West Fisheries Center Review, 1986 (Box 13)
  - South West Fisheries Center Review-Background Material, 1982-1986 (Box 13)
  - State of Illinois Pollution Control Board, 1970-1971 (Box 13)
  - Testimony-Sub-Committee on Air and Water Pollution, 1970 (Box 13)
  - University of Michigan Environmental Studies Task Force, 1991-1992 (Box 13)
  - University of Michigan Environmental Studies Task Force-Reports, 1970-1992 (Box 13)
  - University of Wisconsin-Milwaukee Associate Dean for Research, 1973-1976 (Box 13)
  - Wisconsin Conservation Department Proposal, 1967 (Box 13)